<xml>
<head>
<title>ClanLib API - Overview</title>
<eyecolor>yellow</eyecolor>
</head>
<body>

<p>The overview section is a walkthrough of many of ClanLib's components,
classes and interfaces. It is highly adviceable to read it from the one
end to the other, if you want to get a full overview of what ClanLib can do
for you.</p>

<p>The ClanLib game SDK is a library that can ease your game development in many ways.
ClanLib has APIs for 2D graphics, 3D graphics, sound, network, I/O, input, GUI and
resource administration. Besides, ClanLib reads a number of common image formats, either 
natively or through third-party libraries supported by ClanLib. ClanLib provides transparent 
support for OpenGL, so that you can use native OpenGL commands, while letting ClanLib
handle the boring parts, such as textures, sound, and all the other things that are required 
to make a good game besides 3D graphics.</p>

<p>This overview will describe the components of ClanLib one at a time, without focusing too
much on the actual API (you can use the reference section for that), but instead focusing on
describing what you can use ClanLib for (and also what you can't use it for).</p>

<p>We will assume you're familiar with C++, and basic game programming terminology. If you're 
just starting out on making games, perhaps you should first look at a few of the numerous sites
that describe game programming in general.</p>

<p>If there is something you think is missing out in the documentation,
don't hesitate to point out what you think could be improved. After all,
good documentation at least doubles the value of a library.</p>

<p>(This part is still under construction. Documentation volunteers wanted!)</p>

<menu>
<menuitem "getting_started.html" "Getting started" "The bootstrapping code needed in all ClanLib applications.">
<menuitem "2dapi.html" "The 2D display component" "2D functionality in ClanLib.">
<menuitem "loading_graphics.html" "Loading graphics overview" "A description on how to load graphics with ClanLib.">
<menuitem "resource_overview.html" "Resource overview" "Learn to use the resource system in ClanLib.">
<menuitem "font_overview.html" "Font overview" "Learn how to create and use fonts in ClanLib.">
<menuitem "signals.html" "Signals & Slots overview" "Use a powerful component programming mechanism.">
<menuitem "network_overview.html" "Network overview" "Easy network communication in ClanLib.">
<menuitem "opengl_overview.html" "OpenGL overview" "Using OpenGL with ClanLib.">
<menuitem "gui_overview.html" "GUI overview" "Add GUIs easily to your game with ClanLib.">
<menuitem "engine_design.html" "Game engine design" "Tips on how to make an engine with ClanLib.">
</menu>

</body>
</xml>
